PROFESSOR: So what about
other types of games?
I'm not going to talk about
all kinds of games.
It's going to be a very long time in
this course before we have the
machinery to talk about games
of partial information.
But we can imagine other kinds of
simple, turn-based games where the
layer types are just mixed.
For example, how about backgammon?
What happens in backgammon?
Well, I move, you move, and every time
one of us moves, we roll some dice.
And so in that case, the sequence
of actions is, the maximizing
agent takes an action.
There is some chance outcome, which
in this case is determined by true
randomness, right?
The dice rolling that are
intentionally random.
Then min goes, and then the chance
node will happen again.
You can essentially, when you think
about these trees, you basically just
imagine the environment is one
other player in the game.
It's kind of a random agent that moves
in between the min and max.
How do you compute the
value of this tree?
Well, this is what's called
an Expectiminimax tree.
And what you do is, each node basically
does the same recursion
we've had before.
Max nodes max over their children, min
nodes min over their children, and x
nodes x over their children.
The backgammon case is actually
pretty interesting.
Because you're rolling dice, the
branching factor explodes.
There's all these possible outcomes for
the dice, and that means that even
if you only go down to depth 2, you
already have a huge number of
outcomes, because not only do you have
a lot of moves available to you, but
the dice kind of do their thing.
What this means is a game like this,
where it's not just you and the
opponent moving, but also some element
of chance with many values, it's
really hard to go very
deep into the tree.
So the usefulness of a depth-based
search is really, really low, because
you can't go very far into the future.
On the other hand, the probability of
reaching any particular node is low.
No matter what your plan is, you can't
really guarantee you're going to have
one outcome or another, because the
dice are largely in control.
And that means that limiting depth
is actually less damaging.
There's a historic example here, a
very historic AI called TDGammon,
which used only a depth-2 search, which
is actually already a lot of
computation for backgammon, and a very
good evaluation function that was
tuned through reinforcement learning,
which we'll talk about
later in the course.
And this achieved world champion-level
play in backgammon.
This was the first AI world
champion in any game.
OK.
That's the case when there are
lots of things going on, mins
and maxes and chance.
A very important general case that we
haven't talked about is what happens
if the game isn't zero-sum, or
there are multiple players?
And this turns out to work out as a very
nice generalization of minimax.
So what's shown here is a tree with
three players, red, blue, and green.
And each player is simply out to
maximize their own utility.
They may compete, they may cooperate.
And what this means is we can't get away
with one number and think about
having a max and a min.
Everyone's a max, but they
max their own thing.
And what that means is
with each state--
here the terminal states are shown--
with each state, we associate not a
single utility, but we have to keep
track of how much that state is worth
to each of the possible players.
So for example, if we look down here in
the left, what we would do is you
would say, all right.
At this green node here, what happens?
Well, green's going to look at
these two outcomes, and it's
going to say, all right.
I have a choice of something that's
worth 6 to me and something that's
worth 2 to me.
What am I going to do?
I'm going to pick the
one that's worth 6.
So here this state is worth 1,
6, 6 to those opponents.
Now we chose it because it was
worth 6 to me, and you know,
blue's pretty happy.
We didn't set out to make blue happy.
It just kind of happened because
blue and green want the same
thing at this node.
Red's unhappy.
So in some sense, our behavior actually
shows that we're competing
with red, but we're not doing
it, really, to make red sad.
We're doing it to make
ourselves happy.
The actual numbers in the utility
function suggest that we're
adversaries.
Now what's nice about this is it gives
rise to coordination and cooperation
in a very sophisticated
and elegant way.
And so down here on the left part
of the tree, if you look at the
utilities, you see that green and blue
are basically aligned, and you could
imagine that they're teaming up here.
And in fact, the actions they take
will tend to support each other,
because that's what the utilities say
to do when they do their reasoning.
On the other half of the tree, if you
actually look down here, green and
blue have pretty opposite utilities.
So up here, they're going
to have more competes.
And this notion of competing and
cooperation are just extremes of the
kinds of behaviors that emerge naturally
from these kinds of trees,
and that's pretty cool.
That's a case of complex behavior
emerging from a very simple
computation.